Okay, בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. Today's דף daf is פ Pe 80.
We're a little bit behind first of all also יום העצמאות שמח
Yom Ha'atzmaut Sameach and we pick up in the middle of ע"ט
עמוד ב' Ayin Tet Amud Bet and we're dealing with the issue
about that the husband has the פירות peirot of the נכסי מלוג
nichsei milog of the property in the wife's name of course she
retains title and what to do about certain circumstances where the property
is not a case where the principal remains secure and that it
produces income, transferring it into income producing property and the גמרא Gemara
just dealt with the issue about טיף tif of a flock or
slaves, female slaves, do you take some of the fruit and essentially
reinvest it in the principal because the principal can eventually die. And
that was the debate about whether the woman is entitled to reinvest
that and then the husband would then benefit from the fruit of
what was reinvested,
but that ultimately, you know, this is an area, this is something
where how much you have to do in order to protect the
basic principal.
And then the גמרא Gemara just distinguished and said that the animals
may be different because even if they die you'll still have the
skin, the leather. Of course that's not much of a protection of
principal, the fact that that amount still remains. So we're going to
continue to see that right now. So the גמרא Gemara says like
this: אמר רבנא בר
חייא אמר שמואל, Amar Ravana bar Chiya amar Shmuel, line
14, about 12 lines down, הלכה כחנניה. Halacha ke-Chanania. And חנניה Chanania
basically said that whether it's a case of the maidservants or whether
it's the case of the animals,
he says that it goes to the husband, that it's a normal
case of what you call it, of the husband getting the פירות
peirot even though the principal is somewhat at risk. Okay, so that's
what the גמרא Gemara said before that חנניה Chanania was לא חיישינן
למיתה. lo chashinan le-mita. He's not concerned. Of course though there that's
a case where the principal's risk is very much far in the
future, right, so it's not like fundamentally for the time being the
principal is secure. So there it says we rule like חנניה Chanania
and the product goes to the פירות, peirot, the טיף tif of
the flock goes straight to the husband. So אמר רב אמר רב
נחמן, Amar Rav amar Rav Nachman, אף על גב דאמר שמואל הלכה
כחנניה, af al gav de-amar Shmuel halacha ke-Chanania, although he said like
we rule like
חנניה, Chanania, מודה חנניה שאם נתגרשה נותנת דמים ונוטלתן, modeh Chanania she-im
nitgarsha notenet damim ve-notaltan, that even though the פירות, peirot, the new
sheep or the new children of the female slave go to the
children and they're considered פירות, peirot, that if she gets divorced she
can pay for the baby sheep and she can pay for the
baby slaves and take them back with her. Why? Why does she
have the right to reacquire them? מפני שבח בית אביה, mifnei shevach
beit aviha, a line we're going to see in the next משנה,
mishna,
the praise,
the status of her father's house. That you go, you bring a
flock of sheep, sort of you think of like יעקב Yaakov and
the לבן Lavan story, you bring a flock in with you, then
you leave and you have a much larger flock of sheep. You
don't have the same flock that you started with, you have everything
that produced in the last 20 years. So even though she's going
to have to pay to buy those baby sheep back, but it's
considered the status, you know, it's an important thing for her in
terms of a status issue to be able to take that back
with her. So she has the right to buy that back. אמר
רב אמר רב נחמן, Amar Rav amar Rav Nachman, הכניסה לו עז
לחלבה ורחל לגיזתה ותרנגולת לביצתה. hichnisah lo ez le-chalavah u-rachel le-gizatah ve-tarnegolet
le-beitzatah.
So here we have other things that are not land, that are
similar in that they have a פירות, peirot, but the principal is
not as secure as real estate. Right, real estate always remains, its
value might fluctuate but it always remains,
except after global warming when things will no longer be there. Anyway,
הכניסה לו עז, hichnisah lo ez, so she brings in a goat
for its milk, or a ewe, a lamb for its shearings, or
a hen for its eggs, ודקל לפירותיו, ve-dekel le-peirotav,
or a palm tree for its dates, אוכל והולך עד שתכלה הקרן.
ochel ve-holech ad she-tichleh ha-keren.
So the husband can go ahead and eat, meaning he gets the
פירות, peirot, and he doesn't have to be concerned that the principal
will eventually be destroyed. Okay, so it's like what we said before
about the issue about the sheep, although there we were talking about
babies and here we're talking about other things, right. These are things
that are different than babies, you know, the babies is something that
happens more rarely. These are things that they're regularly producing it, it's
a regular fruit producing tree, it's a regular wool producing thing, it's
a regular egg producing thing, so that is considered like קרקע ופירות
karka ve-peirot and there apparently there's no question that we're not concerned
about the risk to the principal. The husband is entitled to eat
the fruit. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this, one
minute, right, okay, אוכל והולך עד שתכלה הקרן. ochel ve-holech ad she-tichleh
ha-keren.
And רש"י Rashi points out that in all these things even when
it dies there's some remaining value and some remaining to the animal
itself like the leather and whatnot but the גמרא Gemara is spelling
that out. אמר רב נחמן Amar Rav Nachman yeah. Just a second
which category did we cover this? שבח בית אבי? Shevach Beit Avi?
Yeah well I said we're gonna see it in the next משנה.
Mishna. So let's hold off for it okay? אמר רב נחמן עיילא
לגלימי Amar Rav Nachman ayeila leglimei
if she brings in a cloak פירא הוי. peira havei. So using
the cloak is considered its fruit. מיכלי ואזיל עד דכליה. Michlei va-azeil
ad de-kalyah. And she can continue using it even though it wears
away the coat. So here we're dealing with and this is continuing
in that concept
of the sheep and the
lands that even if the principal is not totally protected if there's
something that's considered to be standard פירות perot of the thing the
husband is entitled to use that פירות perot even if the principal
is getting worn away. So the גמרא Gemara says כמאן כי האי
תנא. ke-man ki hai tanna. Who is this going like the following
תנא? tanna? תניא Tanya we saw in a ברייתא baraita המלח והחול
הרי זה פירות. hamelach ve-hachol harei zeh perot.
So again if you have basically a type of a thing where
you dig sand from a certain
ditch or whatever or you have salt that is made because you
have these salt mines that's considered to be פירות. perot. Even though
it is a non-renewable resource like the sand. But anyway these are
non-renewable resources and essentially you're extracting the קרן keren right? I mean
that's the actual land itself after you take it out it doesn't
have it anymore. It's not producing something new you're just extracting what's
there. פירשא גפרית מחפורת של צריף Pirsha gafrit machporet shel tsrif
similarly if you have a ditch a hole that you take from
it. רש"י Rashi says גפרית gafrit was normally
sulfur. רש"י Rashi says אלום. alum. Is אלום alum aluminum?
No aluminum is an alloy right? No sorry about
what?
אלום Alum I don't
know it just calls it אלום alum there. Oh it says here
a note אלום alum is used as a dye for clothes and
soap. Oh dye for clothes and soap. Okay. Or a place where
you remove
oh no רש"י Rashi said גפרית gafrit was אלום. alum. Oh no
I'm sorry you're right רש"י Rashi said צריף tsrif is אלום. alum.
גפרית Gafrit is sulfur. So anyway you have these various mines. רבי
מאיר אומר קרן וחכמים אומרים פירות. Rabbi Meir omer keren va-Chachamim omrim
perot. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says it's the principal similar to the
way he said that the fruit on the tree is the principal
and the חכמים Chachamim say no it's the פירות. perot. And even
the extraction of this is considered פירות perot and that's a big
חידוש chiddush right? So if the woman basically comes in with oil
fields okay all of the oil that's taken out of it is
considered to be the פירות perot and the husband puts it straight
into his pocket even though it's a non-renewable resource and after she
gets divorced it's not like there's more that that same oil is
still there and it's replenished right? So this is a big חידוש
chiddush these whole last cases about what we're willing to consider to
be פירות perot for the benefit of the husband. Even a cloak
until it's reduced to rags is a kind of right same idea
yep.
But okay but there at least in each use you're not taking
and taking away from the thing itself. רבי שמעון אומר מקום שיפה
כחה Rabbi Shimon omer makom she-yifeh kocha so רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon says where he's better when they get married he's
worse when he gets divorced and the reverse by her talking about
whether the fruit on the tree is considered to be part of
the land or not. רבי שמעון היינו תנא קמא Rabbi Shimon hainu
Tanna Kama that's just like the תנא קמא Tanna Kama because the
תנא קמא Tanna Kama basically said that the fruit on the tree
is considered קרקע karka against רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. So the גמרא
Gemara says אמר רבא מחוברים בשעת יציאה איכא בינייהו. Amar Rava mechubarim
be-sha'at yetzi'ah ika beinihu.
No the question is so they agree that when she comes into
the marriage that like the חכמים Chachamim that the פירות perot at
that stage are קרקע karka and then when they come off the
tree they're פירות perot and they go to the husband. The question
is that when she gets divorced. When she gets divorced and there's
fruit on the tree does she say okay this is the thing
I have a title to it includes the fruit on the tree
that's part of the קרקע? karka? That's what the חכמים Chachamim that's
what רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon would say right? That when she came
in it was part of the קרקע karka when she goes out
it's considered part of the קרקע karka so therefore she takes she
doesn't have to pay the husband for the value of the fruit
on the tree. Whereas the גמרא Gemara is saying that that's not
necessarily clear that the חכמים Chachamim would agree with this. The חכמים
Chachamim might say that no when she actually leaves she only has
title to the קרקע karka itself and she actually does have to
pay the husband for the value of the fruit on the tree.
All right so not exactly clear why that would be but the
גמרא Gemara if you take a look רש"י מחוברים בשעת יציאה דאי
אבו רבנן לית להו הא דאמר רבי שמעון בשלה דקסברי מה שגדל
ברשותו שלו. Rashi mechubarim be-sha'at yetzi'ah de-i abu Rabbanan les lehu ha
d'amar Rabbi Shimon beshalah dekasavari mah she-gadal birshuto shelo. Okay
so therefore רש"י Rashi says that here they were married you have
the trees they started getting the apples started coming on the trees
so the husband has rights to those apples because when they were
growing he had rights to the פירות. perot. even though they weren't
picked. So according to the חכמים, Chachamim, it would not be a
parallel. When she comes in, those trees are considered to be the
fruit on those trees are considered to be קרקע, Karka, not פירות,
Peiros, and then when they're plucked they go to the husband. They're
considered to be all פירות Peiros that go to the husband when
they come in and he gets all of them. They at the
time when they came in they were just part of the קרקע.
Karka. But when she goes out, since they grew under his when
they were married, he has the right to demand payment for the
increased value of the land because those fruit grew on it. All
right. So now we move on. Next משנה. Mishna. נפלו לה עבדים
ושפחות. Noflu lah avadim ushfachos. Okay,
so now we have another case here about going on to this
question about when there's an issue of principal
that you know what is what she brings in considered to be
the principal? What's considered the פירות? Peiros? How do you ensure that
it's a type of a of an investment that produces פירות? Peiros?
So she basically has now these slaves. All right. זקנים. Zekeinim. Now
they're old slaves. So if they're old slaves there's no פירות. Peiros.
There is very little or minimal פירות. Peiros. Okay. It's more of
a responsibility than a benefit. So what do you do with it?
ימכרו וילקח בהם קרקע והוא אוכל פירות. Yimachru veyilakach bahem karka vehu
ochel peiros. So you see they have to be sold. Apparently he
can insist on that. That you go ahead and buy the land
so that he's actually able to get. So he acts like a
personal valet? Well the גמרא's Gemara's we're going to see about that
because again the משנה Mishna even if they get slaves. Right. So
let's see what let's see what רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon
ben Gamliel says. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel
omer לא תמכור. lo timkor. No, she cannot be made to sell
them even though it means that the husband doesn't get anything out
of it. מפני שהם שבח בית אביה. mipnei shehem shevach beis aviha.
And that's the line we saw before because they are the praise
of the father's house. The fact that she has these servants does
something for her her status that she has servants even servants that
aren't able to do so much. And he is not allowed to
compromise that just so that he should have the right to have
increased פירות. Peiros. I still don't understand how you disagree. So you
had other משניות Mishnayos that said you know if she has one
servant she doesn't have to do this. That presumably would not be
a זקנים. Zekeinim. Okay. So נפלו לה
זיתים וגפנים. Noflu lah zeisim ugefanim.
So now let's say she has olive trees and and
vines. זקנים Zekeinim and they are old and not producing so much
and the husband wants to take that you know you know to
sell them and get something that will produce more. So ימכרו וילקח
בהם קרקע והוא אוכל פירות. Yimachru veyilakach bahem karka vehu ochel peiros.
Same הלכה. Halacha.
The husband can insist that you invest it in something that will
yield a greater a greater
income even without endangering the principal. רבי יהודה אומר Rebbi Yehuda omer
לא תמכור מפני שהם שבח בית אביה. lo timkor mipnei shehem shevach
beis aviha. And here רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda says goes even further
than רבן שמעון בן גמליאל. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel. It's one thing
to have a whole you know collection of slaves that does something
for your status. But he says even just having vineyards even if
they don't produce so much, you know an olive you know grove,
that also does something for your personal status. Okay. So the גמרא
Gemara says like this. אמר רב כהנא אמר רב Amar Rav Kahana
amar Rav מחלוקת שנפלו בשדה שלה. machlokes shenoflu besadeh shelah.
This is when basically the vines and the it's like I said
vineyards and an olive grove she owns the actual land. So then
it's an issue of her status. אבל בשדה שאינה שלה. aval besadeh
she'eina shelah. Let's say basically she owns olive trees in somebody else's
orchard. Okay. דברי הכל תמכור. divrei hakol timkor.
Everybody would agree she has to sell it because that's not you
know a big status thing and she has no right to object
in that case. Meaning literally the principal will wane, right? דכליה קרנא.
dekalyah karna. We didn't I didn't read those words. Oh I'm sorry.
It's okay. משום דכליה קרנא mishum dekalyah karna because in those cases
so he doesn't just say what I said which is that there's
not not much status to be gained from them. But he actually
says that in that case if you don't have the land if
all you've got is the vine and the vine is basically old
then it's in the process of dying. So she basically can't like
you know then the actual principal is at risk as well. And
if the principal is at risk she can sell. Of course that's
funny because the principal being at risk is her issue, right? The
principal being at risk is is protecting her interests. But she's the
one that doesn't want it sold. So how can you use the
fact that the principal is at risk to force her to sell
it? Like that's suppose you know that's like that's her concern whether
the principal is at risk.
So I don't know. Anyway, but I would just have said that
it's because it's not as much of a status issue. Okay. Anyway,
so
רש״י Rashi says if you look at רש״י, Rashi, דברי הכל תמכור
וילקח בהן קרקע ואין אחד מהם יכול לעכב ממכירתן. divrei hakol timkor
veyilakach bahen karka ve'ein echad mehem yachol le'akev mimchirasun. שאין כאן שבח
בית אביה היכא דכליה קרנא. she'ein kan shevach beis aviha heicha dekalyah
karna. So
רש״י Rashi translates since the principal is at risk and you're not
left with any fields, there's no שבח בית אביה. shevach beis aviha.
Okay. So that's how רש״י Rashi means it. And that's why she
can't object because there's no שבח בית אביה. shevach beis aviha. He
also says neither of them can object. So if she wants to
sell it, he can't object because she can say I'm protecting my
principal, right now the principal is at risk. Okay. So רש״י Rashi
sort of addresses the question I raised in two directions. The fact
that the principal is at risk means he can't object, and the
fact that the principal is at risk turns it into a case
where it's not a status issue and therefore she can't object. Okay.
So the now the גמרא Gemara says like this. מתקיף לה רב
יוסף. maskif lah Rav Yosef. Rav Yosef asks, הרי עבדים ושפחות harei
avadim ushfachos Because he thought שאינה שלו דמי. she'eina shelo dami. How
about the case of slaves? That's like a field that isn't hers
in the sense that after the slave dies, you're not left with
anything. You could say not really, I mean there's a middle case
where the slave is so infirm that there's no פירות perot and
he can't do any work, but he's still alive. But anyway, there's
no, not left with anything, it's כליא קרנא. kalya kerna. ופליגי, u'pligi,
and they disagree. Again you could say that there's a big difference,
that that's a case that there still is שבח בית אבי, shevach
beis avi, but anyway, so it's an interesting comparison. אלא איתמר הכי
איתמר, ela itmar hachi itmar, here's how it was said. אמרי רב
כהנא אמר רב, amre rav kahana amar rav, מחלוקת בשדה שאינה שלו.
machlokes besadeh she'eina shelo.
The debate is when it's not her field and even there there's
a position that it's considered to be שבח בית אבי. shevach beis
avi. אבל בשדה שלו, aval besadeh shelo, if he actually owns the
field itself and that's going to remain even if the vines die,
דברי הכל לא תמכור מפני שבח בית אבי. divrei hakol lo timkor
mipnei shevach beis avi. Everybody would agree that the issue of status
is there and he cannot force her to sell. So we have
a fascinating whole range of things that he's entitled to the income,
but who do you listen to in terms of protecting the principal,
in making sure there's a higher income? We had the discussion before
that if she brings in money to be invested, can you listen
to her if she wants to invest it in a more conservative
investment that more protects the principal? That would win out over him
getting a greater income. We learned just before question that if she
actually brings in not money but she brings in things that are
produced, things like hens that lay eggs and goats that have milk
and other types of things, even though there the principal is at
risk, apparently he can,
she's not entitled to sell it if she wants. It doesn't sound
like it. It sounds like he can say no, I'm going to
keep on getting the milk and the eggs or whatever even though
your principal's at risk and even to the point where we're dealing
with non-renewable resources like extracting oil and extracting ore.
That's considered פירות perot and presumably she is not entitled to say
that I want to sell it and reinvest it. So when you
actually come in with a particular type of an item, there might
be a case where we consider it to be קרן keren and
פירות perot and she cannot force to convert that. And here we
have the case where he can't force her even if it's not
producing a high income, he cannot force her to convert it. Yes.
שבח shevach is an economic term.
Doesn't say רווח. revach. Yeah, שבח בית אבי shevach beis avi does
not here seem to be economic. It seems to be an issue
about status. Right, so dignity. Dignity in a way, right? All right.
Although we had before like if they had that
fishpond kind of thing? Yeah, and we have the מחלוקת machlokes about
the fishpond. Yeah, so תוספות tosafot asks about how that fits into
the fishpond discussion. Okay, next משנה. mishnah. המוציא הוצאות על נכסי אשתו.
hamotzi hotza'os al nichsei ishto.
Now, so that was one thing about what the basic principle in
investment is.
Now what the principal is, what the title is on what type
of property or investment. Now the question is about actually putting money
into the investment. Okay, so how does that work if it's a
field and the husband has to spend ten thousand dollars in terms
of hiring laborers and buying manure and buying seeds and whatever,
so what's the story? So you would say, okay, he makes whatever
risk he wants in terms of the investment and he pockets any
profit, right? And if there's not a profit and it's a loss,
presumably that was his
risk and tough luck. Okay, so let's take a look at what
the משנה mishnah says. המוציא הוצאות על נכסי אשתו. hamotzi hotza'os al
nichsei ishto. So somebody actually spends money, makes out-of-pocket expenses on the
property that his wife owns that he's entitled to get the income
from. הוציא הרבה ואכל קימעא, hotzi harbe ve'achal kima, let's say he
invested a lot of money and he only grossed a very little
amount, so there actually was a net loss. He developed the land?
It could be developed, but it could be that where there's a
lasting benefit in the principal, but it doesn't have to be developed.
It could just be that he planted the seeds and did the
furrows and hired the laborers or whatever and there was a blight
and a drought. And it's about, yeah, he let, I don't know
if I'd call that developing the land. Developing the land has like
an increase in principal. But he invested in it and it was
a net loss. Okay. You know, he had a store and
he owned a Blockbuster right before Netflix came out or whatever.
So whatever it is, he made an investment and there was a
net loss. Okay. Great idea, Alex. Right. הוציא הרבה ואכל קימעא, hotzi
harbe ve'achal kima, or קימעא ואכל הרבה, kima ve'achal harbe, or the
opposite: he made a small investment and it was a huge
growth profit, huge gross, so therefore a big net profit. מה שהוציא
הוציא ומה שאכל אכל. mah shehotzi hotzi u'mah she'achal achal. He's taking
whatever risk. Whatever he invested he invested, whatever he profited he profited.
He's basically entitled to as much profit as he can get out
of it, but he also can't complain if there's a net loss.
He takes the risk and he gets whatever the rewards are. Okay,
that's all, that makes a lot of sense. הוציא ולא אכל, hotzi
velo achal,
now let's say... He invested ten thousand dollars in it and he
has yet to get any, not just profit, any gross אכל, achal,
אכל achal is gross, not profit, not net profit, right? He has
yet to get any benefit. Basically, he planted, he manured, he seeded,
and then he divorced his wife before the harvest season. Okay, so
he didn't get anything out of it. So what does, does he
get back anything for his investment? So the Mishnah says, well, you
could just say that's his risk, but the Mishnah actually says, let's
see what the Mishnah says. It says, well, that's true, you could
always wait to divorce her, but okay, but let's say there's not
only
that, let's, okay, anyway, ישבע כמה הוציא ויטול, yishava kama hotzi veyitol,
then he can take an oath how much he invested and at
least he can get back his investment. Okay, so that's, yeah, I
mean, that's an interesting way of protecting him. It's basically saying that
once he actually reaped something from the investment, even though it wasn't
necessarily a net, it was only your gross, then it was considered
to be like, this is what you got out of your investment.
You made an investment, you're entitled to the returns, so you got
some returns, doesn't matter if it was a net gain or net
loss, you got some returns, that was the exchange essentially, that was
the deal. But if you invested and didn't take out any returns
yet, then all you did was invest money in your wife's property.
You didn't get the אכילת פירות achilat peirot in exchange, so then
you're entitled to get back your investment. Yeah, in some way it
might also refer because you know then that, you know because let's
say like because then he doesn't wait to divorce her anyway so
he can get all the פירות peirot and sell it, right, once
she's divorced? Yeah, that doesn't protect her because as you point out
he could always wait, if it's just about waiting he could always
wait to divorce her. It does protect him because you could imagine
a case where, I mean and we're going to talk about this
in the Gemara, let's say for example, I invested all this money
and there was a huge drought, right, and therefore what I'm going
to do is I'm actually not going to harvest the thing at
all and let it rot because I'd rather let it rot and
be able to take back my investment from my wife, right, rather
than, you know, actually harvest it for the little bit of gross,
you know, for the little bit of gross that I'm going to
get which is far less. So the question is, does when it
says that he was not אוכל, ochel, does it mean he was
not אוכל ochel because they're divorced, or does it mean that he
was like not אוכל ochel because, you know, he's just choosing not
to be אוכל ochel because, you know, because he's going to have
a net loss? If so, there could you could always just do
a large הערמה ha'arama here. Every time it's going to be a
net loss, he'll just choose not to, you know, not to take
the income from it or something like that. It doesn't sound like
that's the case. But also it could allow him to take a
big risk, right? Let's say he can take a huge risk on
the, on his investment even though it might yield zero, right, because
at the end, well, if it yields zero, I'll always be able
to get back to my investment. So it's not a little bit
of a Blockbuster store, right? So it's not so, so fair to
her, you know, in that, in that type of a way. Anyway,
the first time the Mishnah uses the word הוציא hotzi it means
to invest and the last time it uses the word הוציא hotzi
it means to divorce. No, הוציא ולא אכל hotzi velo achal is
the last line. No, it means he invested money and he didn't
get any benefit from it. Then why does Rashi say אם גרשה?
im gersha? Where is the, where is the גרושין? gerushin? Because that's,
because why is it לא אכל lo achal or why is it
ישבע כמה הוציא ויטול? yishava kama hotzi veyitol? So that's what I
wanted to say which is that Rashi, this isn't explicit in the
Mishnah, right, but you could have read it like I said. They're
living together, they're married happily for twenty years, they're not getting divorced
at all. Okay? But he made a huge investment, he lost everything,
he didn't get one penny of gross of any type of a
thing, fine, take an oath and get it all back from his
wife. Okay? That would be a little bit absurd, right, that he
could be entitled to do this especially if they're still married, you
would think it's like an ongoing type of thing, you don't year
by year get to take back, and where does your wife have
money that you're taking the money back from your wife and so
on. So Rashi says, no, no, no, we're not talking about that.
The only reason he would be נשבע nishba and take the money
back out is that now that they're divorced, okay, and that's it.
And it seems therefore that Rashi is reading the scenario of לא
אכל lo achal means לא הספיק לאכול עד שגרשה, lo hispik le'echol
ad shegersha, right?
So that it actually means that the only reason it's לא אכל,
lo achal, he can't just say I'm going to let the stuff
rot in the field, that Rashi is bothered by these issues that
we just read, otherwise it really allows him to manipulate things in
a pretty serious way. So Rashi says, no, as long as they're
married and it's ongoing or whatever, you know, it's year by year,
whatever you invest you invest, you lose or whatever. But the question
is if you got divorced, and not because you just chose not
to take anything from it, but it did not yet produce its,
you know, product yet, in that case you're entitled to get your
investment back. That's how Rashi explains it. Let's see what the Gemara
says. Okay, so the Gemara says וכמה אכילה, vekama achila, so he
has to eat a little bit, so how much is a little?
Meaning, presumably if you got absolutely no benefit, you know, then he
gets his investment back. So how much of a little that says
that was the trade-off and then he doesn't get his investment back?
So וכמה
אכילה אמר רב אסי אפילו גרוגרת אחת, vekama achila amar Rav Assi
afilu grogeret achat, even one little... pressed fig, right? והוא שאכלה דרך
כבוד, Vehuhu she'achala derech kavod, but that's only if he ate it
like in an honorable way, like it was a significant thing, he
wasn't just like snacking it down. I don't know exactly what that
means. Okay. Whole meal? I know whole meal, but anyway. אמר רבי
אבא אמר בי רב, Amar Rabi Abba amar Bei Rav, אפילו שגרא
דתמרי, afilu shigra detamre, even some type of a pressed date. בעי
רביבי, Bei Ravibi, חופצא דתמרי מאי? chuptza detamre mai? How about a
mashed date? תיקו, Teiku, we don't know. Okay. לא אכלה דרך כבוד
מאי? Lo achala derech kavod mai? If he didn't eat it in
a way of כבוד, kavod, what's the story? אמר עולא, Amar Ulla,
פליגי בה תרי אמוראי במערבא, pleigi bah terei amoraei bema'arava, צבו אמוראי
מארץ ישראל דביהוד, tzivu amoraei me'Eretz Yisrael d'beihud, how much would be
a minimum amount if we're just talking about like a dollar value?
חד אמר בכאיסר, chad amar beke'isar, an איסר isar worth, וחד אמר
בכדינר, vechad amar bechedinar, a דינר dinar worth, which is whatever. I
don't know, a dollar, two dollars, five dollars, it's not a lot.
Okay. If that's the amount that he got out of the field,
then he can't get his investment back.
אמי דייני דפומבדיתא, Ami dayanei dePumbedita, so the judges of פומבדיתא Pumbedita
said, עבד רב יהודה עובדא, avad Rav Yehuda uvda, רב יהודה Rav
Yehuda did act on the following thing, בחזילי זמורות, bechazilei zmorot, in
a case of bundles of twigs, that a husband basically just took
a bundle of twigs from the field and you know and that
that and then presumably let's say divorced his wife, reading it like
we just said like רש"י Rashi reads it, and then he said,
oh, you already took a bundle of twigs, you got some benefit
out of the field, you can't get your investment back.
רב יהודה לטעמיה, Rav Yehuda letameih, רב יהודה Rav Yehuda is going
to his reasoning, דאמר רב יהודה, de'amar Rav Yehuda, אכלה ערלה שביעית
וכלאים, achla orla shevi'it vekilayim, if somebody basically was on a field
and ate the produce which was ערלה, orlah, the first three years
where it's אסור בהנאה, assur behana'ah, or שביעית shevi'it where you're not
supposed to you're supposed to make it הפקר, hefker, or כלאים, kilayim,
also אסור בהנאה, assur behana'ah, הרי זו חזקה, harei zu chazakah, that
counts as a חזקה. chazakah. Now how's that relevant? So רש"י Rashi
basically says, because you can't really mean you're eating the ערלה orlah
and the כלאים, kilayim, it must mean what are you eating from
the ערלה orlah tree? It really doesn't mean eating, it means you're
getting the twigs and the wood from the tree or from the
כלאים. kilayim. תוספות Tosafot even there asks, it's not so clear that
the wood from כלאים kilayim is מותר בהנאה, mutar behana'ah, maybe the
wood should be אסור. assur. So anyway, but it's understood to mean
that that's some type of a case of similar that you didn't
actually eat fruit, you just got the twigs, and that's considered to
be like your presence in the land for the idea of חזקה
chazakah of establishing your presence for three years. And here too it's
considered to be that you extracted something from the land, it's something
of significance, and therefore if they got divorced afterwards the wife can
say, you already got some benefit out of this year's produce, and
therefore you cannot get your investment back. מהו חזקה? mahu chazakah? That's
what it means by חזקה. chazakah. חזקה Chazakah is the בבא בתרא
Bava Batra sense, but we're making an analogy. Just like there it's
considered getting benefit to be established your presence for three years, establish
a claim, right? Here too it's getting benefit that you cannot now
you can't claim your investment back. Establishing a claim, right. אמר רבי
יעקב אמר רב חסדא, Amar Rabbi Yaakov amar Rav Chisda, המוציא הוצאות
על נכסי אשתו קטנה, hamotzi hotza'ot al nichsei ishto ktanah, now if
somebody basically invests the money on his wife's property and his wife
is a קטנה, ktanah, not just a קטנה, ktanah, but it's a
קטנה ktanah married off by her mother and her brothers so she
could do מיאון. mi'un. So here we've got this issue. She could
do מיאון, mi'un, okay, he goes ahead and he invests $10,000,
and she's the one now who has the power. So before he
can go ahead and get any benefit out of the oh no,
he gets the first benefit out of the field, she waits for
him to like harvest you know $10 worth, and then she does
מיאון, mi'un, and then she goes ahead and now she's got the
field that's all been increased because of him. And right, and she
was מבטל mevatel the whole thing, okay? So or even if maybe
he can get his investment back because notice this is different. When
she does מיאון mi'un retrospectively the marriage never existed. So retrospectively the
marriage never existed, maybe then she's like a stranger and he just
put money into a stranger's field. So right, understand how that would
work retrospectively? So maybe even maybe he is entitled to get his
investment back, but nevertheless we wanted to protect him so well we'll
talk about that. So the גמרא Gemara says in that case, כמוציא
על נכסי אחר דמי. kemotzi al nichsei acher dami. It is exactly
like this. It is like investing money in a stranger's field. מאי
טעמא? Mai ta'ama? עבדו בה רבנן תקנתא כי היכי דלא נפסידינהו. avdu
bah rabanan takanta ki heichi dela nifsadinehu. The rabbis made a תקנה
takana so he should not waste it, meaning it really was protecting
her in a way, because if he knows that she can divorce
him at any time and I'm gonna lose my investment, he's gonna
make decisions that are gonna minimize his investment and increase what he's
gonna get from the field even at risk of the principal. So
they wanted him, right, because that's your you know the logic, any
dollar I put in is at risk, so let me do what
I can that's the minimum amount of risk even though it might
basically destroy the land, what do I care about the land, I
might not it might not remain mine for long anyway, she might
do מיאון mi'un at any time. So therefore in order to make
make
more prudent decisions they had to protect his interests. Okay, now what
is this idea? And anyway logically it makes sense as המוציא על
הוצאות אחר hamotzi al hotza'ot acher because retrospectively she wasn't his wife.
Okay, although it's actually interesting, there's a famous רב חיים Reb Chaim
that I will go into that there's a question about after a
woman does מיאון, mi'un, how much do we really look at the
past like they were never married? Or do we actually say no,
since at that time it was they were married you know then
that status still obtains at least when we're looking at... backwards as
opposed to looking forwards. Anyway, but here it says it is like
investing in a stranger. Now, what's the הלכה halacha if you invest
in a stranger's land? Exactly. So there's actually a whole סוגיא sugya
about this in other
גמרא, gemara, בבא מציעא Bava Metzia and elsewhere, that if I'm יורד
לתוך שדה חבירו שלא ברשות, yored l'toch s'deh chaveiro shelo b'reshut, I
basically see you've got this great field and nobody is planting it
and there's this great opportunity to plant or whatever and I'm going
to go ahead and plant it without being asked permission. I actually
am entitled, I mean based on certain circumstances, but I'm certainly entitled
to get back my principal, my investment, assuming it doesn't, assuming it's
not more than the benefit you got out of the field. And
in some cases I can even get back more than my investment,
I can even get paid as I was as if I were
a laborer, as if you had hired me.
Basically there you are and you're not mowing your field. You're not
mowing your lawn. It's got all this grass or whatever. I don't,
I knock on the door, nobody answers, you're away on vacation, I
go and I mow your lawn for you. All your neighbors were
saying nasty things anyway. I go and I mow your lawn for
you and I rake your leaves and you come back, I might
be able to say you owe me 40 bucks. That's how much
you pay people to mow your lawn even though you never hired
me. Which is pretty funny, some type of a presumption that no,
normally we would assume you would want to hire somebody for that
even though he did it without actually even being asked. Okay, so
sometimes he's entitled to get back his investment, sometimes he's entitled to
even be paid as a laborer, which is more than just the
actual out-of-pocket cost. So here it says that if a guy does
it to his wife, his קטנה ketannah wife, and he retroactively reverses
the marriage, it would be like he did it for a stranger
and his and his investments would be somewhat protected. So all the
time I continue shoveling the sidewalk in front of my neighbor's house
I can now collect? Yeah. Okay, ההיא איתתא, hahi itteta, now we
have a case, a certain woman, דנפלו לה ארבע מאה זוזי בחוזאי.
d'naflu lah arba me'ah zuzei be-Khuza'i. She had some inheritance of 400
זוז zuz in בחוזאי, be-Khuza'i, which is some, you know, some distant
city
over in Seattle. אזל גברא, azal gavrah, the guy her husband went,
and apparently, I mean based on the story we'll have to assume
he wasn't exactly aware how much the investment was. He heard that
his wife inherited a little, you know, a piece of property somewhere
out in Seattle. So he went there. אזל גברא, azal gavrah, אפיק
שש מאה, afik shesh me'ah, he spent $600 on the plane fare
and the car and the hotel. ואייתי, v'ayti, when he got there
it turned out that the whole thing was only worth $400. אייתי
ארבע מאה, ayti arba me'ah, בארבע מאה, be-arba me'ah,
so then he sold it, whatever, it was a car, whatever it
was that was there waiting for her, he cashed it in and
got 400 bucks and he brought it back. Okay? So he got
obviously there was a net loss here. Okay? ובהדי דקא אתי, v'hadei
d'ka ati, as he was coming back, אצטריך ליה חדא זוזא. itztarikh
leh chada zuza. So on the plane they now don't give you
even peanuts on some flights, so he had to spend $2 out
of the 400 because he was hungry to buy himself some peanuts
on the plane. Okay? So you like how I make this contemporary?
So of the $400 that he got out of it he spent,
he spent a buck. Okay? חדא זוזא, chada zuza, ושקל מנייהו, v'shakal
minaihu,
he didn't have any cash on him so he took from the
$400 he got from the for for selling the car. Okay. אתא
קמיה דרב אמי. ata kamei d'Rab Ami. So now it came to
רב אמי. Rab Ami. אמר ליה רב אמי, amar leh Rab Ami,
רב אמי Rab Ami said, מה שהוציא הוציא ומה שאכל אכל. mah
she-hotzi hotzi u-mah she-achal achal. He spent $600, he got some benefit
from it, okay, and he's not he's now the loss is the
loss. Okay? He looked at the $400 as פירות, peirot, the $600
as investment. So since he got some type of a benefit from
it, he benefited a dollar, so he can't ask for his investment
back. Okay? And he's now out 200 bucks. Okay? Or no, or
actually I take that back. He didn't look at the $400 as
the פירות. peirot. He looked at the $1 as the פירות. peirot.
The $1 that he used essentially for the peanuts. He looked at
that as the פירות. peirot. Okay? So presumably she would get the
$399, he got the $1 and he can't get his investment back.
He just got peanuts. Exactly. אמרו ליה רבנן, amru leh rabanan, so
the rabbis say back to him, לרב אמי, l'Rab Ami, הני מילי
היכא דאכל פירות. hanei mili heicha d'achal peirot. That would be if
he actually got some fruit from it. This wasn't an invest this
wasn't like the investment in the principal and then getting the fruit
that the principal produced. This was an investment to retrieve the principal
and what he got was the principal.
הא קרנא קא אכיל, ha karna ka achil, וצאה v'otza'ei and, you
know, and
money that he spent to retrieve the principal. הוי ליה הוציא ולא
אכל. havi leh hotzi velo achal. He didn't get any fruit from
his investment. If basically the 400 זוז zuz he then used to
buy something and he got some fruit from it, then the $600
maybe to retrieve the principal would be seen as an investment eventually
towards what later would come out out of it, right? So if
basically somebody went and he spent $600 to get something and that
thing later, you know, I don't know, let's say it wasn't just
cash, I don't know what it was, it was a tiny little
piece of land that had been valued at $400 and he went
there to work with the lawyers and he spent $600 to deal
with. of all of those expenses to make sure that the title
was secure, and then later the land was worth ten thousand, so
the six hundred would be considered an investment and the increase would
be considered the פירות. peirot. But that's not here, here he just
retrieved the principal, there was no פירות. peirot. אי הכי הוי ליה
הוציא ולא אכל ישבע כמה הוציא ויטול. Ei hachi havei lei hotzi
velo achal yishava kama hotzi veyitol. So basically he can swear how
much he did and he can retrieve it. Of course, can he
get six hundred dollars back? So no, I mean Rashi here I
think says that he can't take back more than the thing was
actually worth. He can't get his wife to pay him six hundred
dollars for something that was only four hundred. Let me take a
look, I think Rashi says that explicitly. Rashi says...
Rashi doesn't say...
Rashi doesn't say it, but I think we have to assume that
he cannot actually get the full six hundred back. Maybe I saw
it in the Rosh. Hold on one minute. Is a dividend of
money considered פירות? peirot? Yeah, money can be פירות peirot on money,
money generates money, so the generated money is פירות. peirot. Yeah. So
the
Rosh says... the Rosh says like this: ויטול עד שיעור שבח דשמינן
כמה הוו שוין ארבע מאה זוזי דשתא בקורא מאי הוו שוין ולא
יותר. Veyitol ad shiur shevach deshaiman kama havu shavin arba meah zuzei
deshta bekora mai havu shavin velo yoter.
So the Rosh says obviously he cannot take out more than the
thing is worth, so the wife can't lose as a result. Okay,
is that clear? So he cannot actually and by the way, that
goes back to the point I made and I want us to
stop there for a moment as well because we said in the
משנה mishnah that Rashi said they were divorced and that's when he's
taking an oath. This case does not sound like they're divorced, right?
Sounds like they're married, he went to retrieve it, and whatever. So
first of all, it's important to note that this case sounds like
they're not divorced, but the Rosh here stops and makes the point
that he cannot take out more than he actually increased the value.
So that also then goes back and that protects the wife's interests,
right? In the case of divorce, it may be increase the value,
he didn't get a chance to reap the harvest, so he says
he can take an oath how much he invested. But in the
scenarios we discussed, it applies not just to a case of divorce,
so he basically invested ten thousand dollars and the field didn't produce
anything. Now he can make his wife pay him ten thousand dollars?
So the Rosh says no, no, no. What he can take back
out, if for some reason it didn't, you know, he wasn't אוכל,
ochel, you know, what he can take out is limited by the
actual increase in value. He cannot make his wife pay him for
expenses that exceed the value. So in this case, he can take
the four hundred dollars back and it's all a big break-even. All
right? So is that clear? So here we have a case where
there was... so if he didn't... if he put in four hundred
dollars and he wasn't able to, he didn't get the chance, and
it increased by ten thousand dollars, then he gets four hundred dollars.
If he put in four hundred dollars and it didn't increase at
all and they didn't get divorced and they're still married or they
did get divorce, whatever, but this case sounds like they didn't get
divorced. He put in four hundred, he put in six hundred dollars
and he only retrieved four hundred out of it, right? So they're
still married or whatever, but he just now this was money down
the drain, so then basically he can get his investment back up
to the point that, you know, that his... without his six hundred
dollars his wife wouldn't have had the property at all, right? So
now he can get at least four hundred dollars of that six
hundred back. His wife doesn't lose out, she doesn't have to pay
more than she gained from the property and he's able to recoup
his investment to the point, you know, at up to limited by
the actual increase in value. Limited by the benefit. And if they
did get... if they didn't get divorced? Well, it would be the
same thing. But I'm just saying it's important to note in this
scenario that it does not at all sound like they got divorced
and he's still able to do this if there were no פירות.
peirot. But again, it's important to say if that's true in terms
of talking about protecting the wife, it's important to emphasize that he
cannot get out more than he increased the value of this property.
So she has four hundred, he took six hundred of his own
or? Yeah, of his own. Okay. So what's the relationship between the
six hundred of his own and the four hundred that she? He
needed to spend six hundred dollars to retrieve a piece of property
that was only worth four hundred dollars. So she now got access
to a four hundred dollar piece of property, right?
And because of his six hundred dollar investment. Okay, and then he
turned her four hundred dollars into a piece of land. Right. Or
whatever, whatever he did to it, okay, but it made it accessible
to her. Okay. So he's not considered to have been אוכל פירות
ochel peirot because the property didn't produce any פירות. peirot. It wasn't
an investment that produced פירות, peirot, it was an investment that retrieved
the property. Right. And he used his money to buy the פירות...
peirot... no, that wasn't... no, that was פירות peirot is the conclusion.
That was just cutting into the principal. But it didn't produce any
פירות, peirot, so therefore he's entitled to retrieve his investment. Again, it's
a case where sounds... maybe they did get divorced, but it doesn't
sound like it. It just sounds like it was money that was
sunk in a hole that didn't produce any פירות peirot and nevertheless
he can retrieve his investment but only up to the actual increase
in value of the property. Let's go on. ישבע כמה הוציא ויטול.
Yishava kama hotzi veyitol. He should swear how much he invested, again
in this case where he did not eat the פירות peirot and
maybe also they got divorced according to Rashi, and take back... what
he invested again limited by the increase of the value of the
property. אמר רב אסי amar Rav Asi והוא שיש שבח v'hu sheyesh
shevach and here we go. והוא שיש שבח כנגד הוצאה. v'hu sheyesh
shevach k'neged hotza'a. And that's only if the actual increase of the
value of the property is equivalent or more or maybe more, at
least it's equivalent to the actual investment. But if the increase is
less than the investment, he can't make her lose as a result.
Okay, למהי הלכתא, l'mai hilchata, for what point are you making this
הלכה, halacha, meaning we can look at two scenarios: one where the
investment is greater than the increase, which is presumably what it's coming
to exclude, that he's not allowed to take that money out if
it was money down the drain. And the other is that the
investment is less than the increase. So let's take a look. אמר
אביי amar Abaye שאם היה שבח יתר על ההוצאה, she'im haya shevach
yeter al hahotza'a, if the increase in value exceeded the investment, נוטל
את ההוצאה בלא שבועה. notel et hahotza'a belo shvu'a. So he's saying
he only needs an oath when he's coming to extract the full
amount that he invested. Okay, I'm sorry, when it's a break-even case,
when his investment exactly equaled the increase in value so she doesn't
leave with any money in her pocket, any additional money in her
pocket. But if the investment was less than the increase so she
had some net gain, so since she's getting some net gain out
of it, he doesn't have to make a שבועה, shvu'a, he can
just say here's how much I spent on it. Of course, the
obvious response is אמר ליה רבא amar leh Rava אם כן אתי
לארומי, im ken ati l'arumei, then he's going to deceive. Basically, the
increase was a thousand. He spent eleven hundred. Or no, whatever, the
increase was a thousand, he spent five hundred. But you know what
he's going to say? I spent nine hundred and ninety-eight dollars. So
as long as he doesn't have to make a שבועה shvu'a when
the investment is a little bit less than the increase, he'll always
say he spent right up to a dollar less than the actual
increase in value and he'll be believed without a שבועה. shvu'a. That's
just a lie, that's the assumption.
Yeah, but that's why you make a שבועה. shvu'a. The שבועה shvu'a
is what you had before you had to produce receipts. Okay.
Basically, imagine, you got to produce receipts to get reimbursed. Okay, but
if you don't have receipts and you don't have evidence, what do
you do? You make a שבועה shvu'a how much you invested. Do
receipts exist for penny expense accounts? Okay, so that's it. So that's
the concern. Are you padding the expense accounts? How do we trust
you? You make a שבועה. shvu'a. So if you don't have to
make a שבועה, shvu'a, you don't have to produce receipts until it
equals the investment, then you're just going to claim that it was
right up to the cost of the investment. אתי לארומי. ati l'arumei.
So the גמרא Gemara says אלא אמר רבא ela amar Rava שאם
הייתה הוצאה יתירה על השבח she'im hayta hotza'a yetira al hashevach אין
לו אלא הוצאה שיעור שבח. ein lo ela hotza'a shiur shevach. No,
what it's coming to say is, and this is what we were
saying before, he always has to make a שבועה shvu'a to get
out because otherwise he'll be lying how much he spent. But if
he actually spent more than the increase, he's not entitled to get
back the amount that went beyond the increase. He was not entitled
to take back his expenses
that result in a net loss to the woman. שאם הייתה הוצאה
יתירה על השבח, she'im hayta hotza'a yetira al hashevach, if the investment
was greater than the increase in value, אין לו אלא הוצאה שיעור
שבח, ein lo ela hotza'a shiur shevach, he's only entitled to his
investment up to the increase in value of the principal. ובשבועה, u'vshvu'a,
and he always has to make a שבועה. shvu'a. Okay, which is
what we said before, which should be obvious. איבעיא להו, iba'ya lehu,
they asked the question: בעל שהוריד אריסין תחתיו מהו? ba'al shehorid arisin
tachtav mahu?
So basically, the husband went ahead and he got some sharecroppers to
go to this land. He says, this is the land is my
wife's נכסי מלוג, nichsei melog, I'd like to hire you as sharecroppers,
go ahead plant it, harvest it, or whatever, you'll take half of
the
פירות peiros and I'll take the other half. Okay, and he went
ahead and he did this and the sharecroppers now spent all of
their out-of-pocket expenses with some manure and the plowing and the work
and the seeds. And then before the harvest season, guess what the
husband did? He divorced his wife.
So, okay, he hasn't spent a penny on the sharecroppers because his
deal with the sharecroppers is you know how he pays them? They
get half of the produce. So he hasn't spent the money, a
penny. So the wife has the property of greatly increased value and
the sharecroppers get zippo. Okay, or do they get zippo? Can they
now go to the wife and say, we increased your property, we're
still entitled to half of the produce. The husband hasn't spent anything,
so what's going to happen to the poor sharecroppers? Shouldn't he go
to the husband? He's the one... Okay, so what's going to happen
to the poor sharecroppers? So let's take a look.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this: בעל שהוריד אריסין תחתיו מהו,
ba'al shehorid arisin tachtav mahu, אדעתא דבעל נחית, ada'ata d'ba'al nachit,
were they basically making a deal with the husband and therefore, like
the way תוספות Tosafot spells it out, they understood presumably they have
to have known that it was נכסי מלוג nichsei melog of their
wife, he obviously deceived them. But assuming they knew it was נכסי
מלוג, nichsei melog, they assumed that risk. They knew, right, that the
husband their deal is with the husband but they knew that the
husband would only be אוכל פירות ochel peiros if he would remain
married to the wife through the time of the harvest. Mean they
have to do a title search. Yeah, but the funny thing... Okay,
so anyway, right, basically... Well, that's a question. I think we're assuming
that they knew it was נכסי מלוג. nichsei melog. That's a good
question, maybe they have to, it's their responsibility to find out, but
let's assume they knew it was נכסי. nichsei. Okay, so they understood
that it was a deal with the husband and that the husband
also would only get the פירות peiros if he would not divorce
his wife. So therefore הסתלק ליה בעל הסתלקו להו, histalek lei ba'al
histalku lehu, if the husband is removed, they are removed. The husband
loses out the פירות, peiros, they lose out the פירות peiros as
well, because that was the deal with the husband. או
דלמא, o dilma, or do we say אדעתא דארעא נחית? ada'ata de'ara
necheis? No, they're not really making a deal with the husband. They're
really, you know, having a relationship with the land. And essentially they're
increasing the land and what they're entitled to because, you know, that's
what fields are like made for, you know, to assume that somebody's
going to plant them and plow them and there's some type of
nice of like a natural law type of an idea here or,
you know, natural that you increase the value of the land, you
work it or whatever, that gives you a certain right to what
the land produces. It doesn't really matter who the owner is, you
know, and therefore you're entitled to get your your portion out of
the land because you worked it, right? And I think that there's
something about the fact that it's an אריס aris relationship, a sharecropper
relationship, which has to do with I invested in the land, I
take out of it as opposed to if it was like a
שכירות sechirut relationship, I was just paying you as a day laborer,
then their relationship would totally be like with the husband, you know.
Okay, yeah, but it depends on on what your deal was. Like,
you know, if you made a better deal for them than the
average sharecropper, you should at least have to pay the difference. Okay,
I mean, the גמרא gemara doesn't get into that, but let's take
a look. או דלמא אדעתא דארעא נחית וארעא כי קיימי לאריסי קיימי.
o dilma ada'ata de'ara necheis ve'ara ki kaimei la'arisei kaimei. The land
is considered to be like like wait like, you know, there for
sharecroppers. It's like it's just, you know, we're waiting for sharecroppers to
come and work it. So essentially their work of it entitles them
even if they never made a deal with the woman. Okay, so
מה סבר, ma savar, so so what do we say? מה סבר
או דלמא אדעתא דארעא נחית. ma savar o dilma ada'ata de'ara necheis.
So מתקיף לה רב פפא בר נחמני, matkif lah Rav Pappa bar
Nachmani, so רב פפא בר רב חנא Rav Pappa bar Rav Chana
asked, excuse me, he asked, I mean, how can you ask I
guess that question? So he says I don't understand your question. Classic
Jewish thing like you're not going to give me an answer, you're
going to ask about my question. מאי שנא מהיורד לתוך שדה חברו
ונטעה שלא ברשות? mai shna mehoyored letoch sdei chavero unata'ah shelo birshut?
I mentioned this to you before. I go into your field and
I plant it and you never gave me any permission, I'm just
doing it unilaterally. שמין
לו וידו על התחתונה. shamin lo veyado al hatachtona. So you estimate
the, you know, investment and expenses and I have the lower hand,
which basically means that, you know, I might only be able to
extract my maybe I can't demand payment as a as a sharecropper
or as a higher hand, but at least I can get back
the money I invested in it, depends on the circumstances. That's like
a whole בבא מציעא Bava Metzia discussion I don't want to go
into. Okay, but basically I'm entitled to at least something back out
of it. So his question is you gave two alternatives. Either they
get zero because the husband gets zero,
or they get the normal sharecropper arrangement. But why is it zero?
Even if the woman, even if there had been no husband and
they just went into this woman's field and planted it without any
permission, at least they'd be entitled to take out their investment. So
why is it either zero or the sharecropper arrangement? They at least
should get their investment.
How is it that they're doing worse than just going into a
stranger's land and planting it? So the גמרא gemara says, no. התם
ליכא איניש דטרח הכא איכא בעל דטרח. hatam leika inish detarach hacha
ika ba'al detarach. So no,
there nobody was working the land. So nobody was working your field
and I go and I plant it, basically we can sort of
say it's clear I objectively did you a טובה. tova. Maybe I
can't charge my normal going rate because that would require a contract
that you hired me, but the fact that I did you a
טובה, tova, that the land was lying fallow, at least entitles me
to recoup my investment, to take something out of it. That's when
I go with a stranger, nobody's working the land. But here the
woman could say to them, you know what the woman could say
to these sharecroppers? You're not entitled, oh you came whatever and did
this land and I owe you something. No, if you hadn't done
it, my husband would have done it.
Okay, and if he would have done it and then divorced me,
I wouldn't have to pay him anything, right? Because it was הוציא
ולא אכל. hotzi velo achal. So therefore I have no obligation to
you, you didn't do me any benefit. Talk to my husband. Exactly.
But it depends on how much he could have done. If something
was too much for one person to do... Alright, so right, well
let's take a look, that's going to be the גמרא's gemara answer.
But this is also interesting because it also gets to this question
of how much is it like there's a sense of like the
טובה tova that I did to you or how much is it
the objective reality that I improved your land, you know, entitles me
to something. So let's take a look. So אמר רב הונא בריה
דרב יהושע, amar Rav Huna breih deRav Yehoshua, מה הוי עלה, ma
hava ala, what was the conclusion? אמר רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע
חזינא. amar Rav Huna breih deRav Yehoshua chazina. We look at it.
אי בעל אריס הוא, ei ba'al aris hu, oh like Michael said,
if the husband himself is a sharecropper, so he could have worked
the land, then they have no claim on the woman because she'll
say my husband would have worked the land. הסתלק ליה בעל הסתלקו
להו. histalek lei ba'al histalku lehu. And basically in terms of answering
the prime first question, yes, their deal was with the husband. And
they can't say like ארעא לאריסות קיימא, ara le'arisut kaima, no, there's
an objective reality that anybody, you know, that me it was waiting
for people to come to work it. You know who was waiting
to come to work it? The husband. The husband could have worked
it. So therefore them putting themselves in there doesn't fundamentally entitle them.
anything. And presumably they get zero, they don't even get their investment.
But אי בלאו אריסו, ee b'lav arisu, but if the husband was
not in the position to do it himself and somebody else has
to do it, then that case ארעא לאריסותא קיימא ara l'arisusa kaima
then they not only are they entitled to their investment, they're entitled
to their sharecropper arrangement because then somebody had to do it and
the somebody normally would be like the sharecropper that's seen again not
as a hired hand but as a relationship with the land and
therefore you come and you work there as a sharecropper, you're actually
entitled to their at the normal rate as a sharecropper, okay. But
presumably it's also because the husband made that deal. So if they
just would have gone without any deal then maybe it would have
only been their investment. Why use the word איסתלק, istalek, why the
term איסתלק, istalek, what do you mean? I don't know. He removed
himself from the picture. He no longer is entitled to anything. What
do you mean by by divorce? Yes, because he's divorced. Oh, איסתלק
istalek in this sense means he's divorced. Yes. Yeah, but the word
איסתלק istalek can also can apply to the to the sharecroppers, okay?
if they're like if they're considered if they're like if they're exactly,
exactly. איבעיא להו: בעל שמכר קרקע לפירות, מהו? ibaya lehu: baal she-machar
karka l'peiros, mahu?
Let's say the husband wants to go ahead and sell his right
in the land. I own my wife's property for its פירות. peiros.
I'm going to now go ahead and sell to Michael here the
right that I have in my wife's property. Why not?
Right? So I'm only entitled to פירות. peiros. The גוף guf remains
with the title, but I own it לפירותיה. l'peiroseha. So I'm going
to sell you that זכות, zechus, right? Why not? Why rather than
taking the income every single year, I'll just make a nice big
lump sum and sell to somebody else. He'll lose his rights if
I get if I divorce my wife, but for the time that
we're married, he keeps he's the one that eats the פירות. peiros.
Right. So
I don't know about that, but anyway, okay. מאי? מי אמרינן מה
דקנה אקני? mai? mi amrinan mah d'kana akni? what he owns he
sold? או דילמא כי תקינו ליה רבנן פירות לבעל, משום רווחא דביתא?
o dilma ki tikinu lei rabanan peiros l'baal, mishum revacha d'beisa? No,
when why does the husband have this right? That משום רווחא דביתא.
mishum revacha d'beisa.
That is because of the sort of increase in the house, meaning
the fact that there's a steady income into the house, right, is
a nice way of giving us a more sense, we've got some
nice annual, you know, our annual income is more, we don't have
to scrimp, we can go out to the movies every now and
then, go out to dinner every now and then, right?
peanuts? peanuts, when you're on a flight, I can buy some peanuts.
Okay, so that's רווחא דביתא. revacha d'beisa. That is when you have
a regular income-producing thing on a regular basis. אבל לזבוני, לא. aval
l'zabuni, lo. It wasn't meant for him to just get a nice
lump sum in his pocket and put it away in a bank
account. Yeah, I'll put it in a lump sum, I know, but
the Rav says it's human nature. I'll put it away in my
bank account and I don't want to touch it, okay? Or I'll
spend it all on a Ferrari. That's not the same as a
regular, you know, slight increase in our annual income which is going
to mean that we'll spend we'll have a little bit more freedom
in terms of our regular types of of expenses. Okay? So maybe
they did not give it to him for a purpose of being
of a lump sum increase. They gave it to him for a
for an annual like an ongoing, you know, increase in the income.
And what does he set up the פירות peiros towards what? Oh,
so the פירות peiros are תחת tachas the what do you call
the פדיון pidyon I think, that he would have to redeem her
if she got taken captive or something. So anyway, part of this
question also can be which came up before by the way about
him preventing a sale and all those other issues, if you want
to know the conceptual legal way of framing it, is does he
just like like is it like it's her פירות peiros but he
basically gives them to him, he has the זכות zechus to or
a right to collect the פירות, peiros, or does he actually own
the land לפירותיו? l'peirosov? It's like a קנין לפירות. kinyan l'peiros. So
he actually has like a legal right, a legal קנין kinyan that
he can transfer. Now generally we assume he has a legal קנין
kinyan and the גמרא gemara whole discusses it with קנין פירות כקנין
הגוף דמי, kinyan peiros k'kinyan haguf dami, exactly. So here would actually
be a חידוש chiddush that even though he legally does have title,
we won't let him transfer the title, because we only gave him
the title, it's not full title, it's title לפירות, l'peiros, but we
only gave it to him for a certain purpose. Okay? Well that's
the question. So if we gave it to him because it had
this basic, you know, sort of salutary benefit to the to the
marriage, it wasn't just for him, it was like it was good
for the household to have this type of an arrangement, so even
though he has that title, he'll have it with certain limits. He
won't have it with the same normal types of rights that you
would because we have to we want it to have this type
of a function. But it's not like because she's his שבויה shvuyah
and it's the obligation he has for her, so it's totally his
benefit, doesn't it sound like that? Yeah, but maybe again with these
other aspects to it. So let's take a look. אבל לזבוני לא,
aval l'zabuni lo, but not just for not just for the sake
of sale. Let's get to the משנה. mishnah. יהודה מר בר מרמר
משמיה דרבא אמר מה שעשה עשוי. Yehuda Mar Bar Marmar mishmei d'Rava
amar mah she-asah asui. Yeah, בדיעבד b'di'eved it is good. Maybe it's
not ideal, but it's good. It works. רב פפא אמר משמיה דרבא
לא עשה ולא כלום. Rav Pappa amar mishmei d'Rava lo asah v'lo
klum. It doesn't work. He doesn't have a right to transfer. אמר
רב פפא: הא דיהודה מר בר
מרמר amar Rav Pappa: ha d'Yehuda Mar Bar Marmar blah blah blah.
That's what יהודה בר מרמר Yehuda Bar Marmar said that it works,
לאו בפירוש איתמר אלא מכללא. lav b'peirush itmar ela miklala. It wasn't
said explicitly it was inferred. דההיא איתתא דאייתי ליה לגבי תרתי אמהתא.
d'hahu itesa d'aysi lei legabi tartai amhasa. A certain woman brought into
the marriage... two maidservants and normally when you say brought in it
means like in the נדוניא nedunya the dowry but then it would
fully transfer title so here it doesn't mean that she retained the
title to this but she's coming with her two maidservants that she
still owns or her two slaves she still owns but they're considered
you know he gets the פירות peirot so he gets the benefit
of their service.
After that he went and married a second wife he didn't divorce
the first one then he married a second one and he basically
said to his second wife hey honey come marry me I got
this maid this female slave that can actually help you out with
the housework and I'm entitled to her work because it's from the
פירות peiros from my first wife so that's a good reason to
come marry me. So okay
so he came to Rava אתא לקמיה דרבא. ata lekamei deRava. צווחה!
Savcha! So she the first wife cried out look what he's doing
he's taking this and he's giving it to the second wife so
this is like selling the גוף לפירות guf l'peirot because you're giving
the second wife the right the ownership of the slave for her
service his what he had in that slave. לא אשכח בה. Lo
ashchak bah. Rava ignored her. מן דחזא סבר משום דסבר מה שעשה
עשוי. Man dechaza savar mishum desavar ma she'asa asuy. So it seems
like Rava held that it works he can sell the גוף לפירות.
guf l'peiros. ולא היא Velo hi but that would be actually be
wrong Rava doesn't hold that he or doesn't hold it as a
general rule but it's משום רווח ביתא. mishum revach beisa. Really he
holds that it's not
good because we want the benefit the regular benefit of the house
to keep this as an annual producing income. דהא רווחא Deha ravcha
but in this case it is because even though she's working for
the other wife she's still working in the house she's doing housework
in the kitchen and the cleaning and the cooking and it's not
really selling it outside of the house but to sell it outside
of the house and have a lump sum that just goes into
the bank account that's a different story. והלכתא ולא היא דכל שמכר
נכסיו לפירות לא עשה ולא כלום. Vehilchasa velo hi dechal shemachar nechasav
l'peiros lo asa velo klum. It doesn't work at all but now
we're going to introduce a new reason. מאי טעמא Mai ta'ama why
not? אביי אמר
חיישינן שמא תחסיס. Abaye amar chashinan shema tachsise. We're afraid that he
will come to basically that
destroy the land. I go ahead and I sell the land to
somebody else לפירות l'peiros for that other party they're going to like
you know like like squeeze the land dry they're going to try
to get the maximum amount of פירות peiros in the minimum amount
of time right? They're not in it for the long term game
because the husband could divorce his wife at any moment so they're
that's why it doesn't work because we have to protect the wife's
principal which was the reason we had before. Well I don't know
but he has a new reason okay he says no it's not
because of משום רווח ביתא mishum revach beisa it's to protect the
wife's principal the husband is the one so we assume he's in
it for the long term and he's going to make wise decisions
but to some third party and and he could lose it at
any time he's going to ring it dry so we're afraid he's
going to ruin the land. רבא אמר משום רווח ביתא. Rava amar
mishum revach beisa. No for the reason we said we want the
household to have an regular ongoing income. ותחסיס V'tachsise like to destroy
like to destroy the land.
So what? It's even weakened? Yeah it's to destroy. איכסוף Ichsaf means
to be embarrassed that's like some type of the wife yeah it's
like a turning pale exactly like I said like squeeze it dry.
Okay מאי בינייהו mai beinayhu what would be a difference?
איכא בינייהו ארעא דמקרבא למתא. Ika beinayhu ara demekarva l'masa. Let's say
the land is close to the city so the husband can keep
an eye on it so basically he like he'll prevent the guy
from from misusing it because it's nearby and he can keep an
eye on it. אי נמי בעל אריס Inami ba'al aris or the
husband is an אריס aris what difference does that make? So the
way the ראש Rosh says it a little different than רש"י Rashi
is he knows the business and since the husband knows the business
he'll also be able to keep an eye on it and prevent
the guy from squeezing it dry. Okay אי נמי inami or here's
a different the other way זוזי וקעביד בהו עסקא. zuzei veka'avid behu
iska.
Let's say it is money let's say he wants to go ahead
and take the money right? And he wants to invest it. Right
so then he's not just putting it away in a bank. He
says no no no I'm going to sell it and I'm going
to put it in this nice bonds that's going to produce say
six percent and we'll use the six percent and we'll use the
six percent for משום רווח ביתא mishum revach beisa so then that
according to that approach that would be okay. Alright end here.